<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document url="index.html">

  &project;

  <properties>
    <author email="craigmcc@apache.org">Craig R. McClanahan</author>
    <author email="remm@apache.org">Remy Maucherat</author>
    <author email="yoavs@apache.org">Yoav Shapira</author>
    <author email="jfclere@apache.org">Jean-Frederic Clere</author>
    <title>Documentation Index</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="Introduction">

<p>This is the top-level entry point of the documentation bundle for the
<strong>JBoss Web</strong> Servlet/JSP container, which is based on the 
Apache Tomcat 6.0 project developed by the Apache Software Foundation.
JBoss Web implements the Servlet 3.0 and JavaServer Pages 2.2 specifications from the
<a href="http://www.jcp.org">Java Community Process</a>, and includes many
additional features that make it a useful platform for developing and deploying
web applications and web services.</p>

<p><strong>JBoss Web 7.0.x</strong> is a subsystem of AS7, there isn't yet standalone version of it.</p>

<p>Select one of the links from the navigation menu (to the left) to drill
down to the more detailed documentation that is available.  Each available
manual is described in more detail below.</p>

</section>


<section name="JBoss Web User Guide">

<p>The following documents will assist you in downloading, installing
JBoss Web, and using many of its features.</p>

<ol>
<li><a href="introduction.html"><strong>Introduction</strong></a> - A
    brief, high level, overview of JBoss Web.</li>
<li><a href="sysprops.html"><strong>System Properties</strong></a> - System
    properties used for JBoss Web configuration.</li>
<li><a href="appdev/index.html"><strong>First web application</strong></a>
    - An introduction to the concepts of a <em>web application</em> as defined
    in the <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/servlet/download.html">Servlet
    3.0 Specification</a>.  Covers basic organization of your web application
    source tree, the structure of a web application archive, and an
    introduction to the web application deployment descriptor
    (<code>/WEB-INF/web.xml</code>).</li>
<li><a href="deployer-howto.html"><strong>Deployer</strong></a> -
    Operating the JBoss Web Deployer to deploy, precompile, and validate web
    applications.</li>
<li><a href="realm-howto.html"><strong>Realms and Access Control</strong></a>
    - Description of how to configure <em>Realms</em> (databases of users,
    passwords, and their associated roles) for use in web applications that
    utilize <em>Container Managed Security</em>.</li>
<li><a href="security-manager-howto.html"><strong>Security Manager</strong></a>
    - Configuring and using a Java Security Manager to
    support fine-grained control over the behavior of your web applications.
    </li>
<li><a href="class-loader-howto.html"><strong>Classloading</strong></a>
    - Information about class loading in JBoss Web, including where to place
    your application classes so that they are visible.</li>
<li><a href="jasper-howto.html"><strong>JSPs</strong></a>
    - Information about Jasper configuration, as well as the JSP compiler
    usage.</li>
<li><a href="ssl-howto.html"><strong>SSL</strong></a> -
    Installing and
    configuring SSL support so that your JBoss Web will serve requests using
    the <code>https</code> protocol.</li>
<li><a href="rewrite.html"><strong>URL Rewriting</strong></a> -
    Using rewriting features in JBoss Web.</li>
<li><a href="proxy-howto.html"><strong>Proxy Support</strong></a> -
    Configuring JBoss Web to run behind a proxy server (or a web server
    functioning as a proxy server).</li>
<li><a href="default-servlet.html"><strong>Default Servlet</strong></a> -
    Configuring the default servlet and customizing directory listings.</li>
<li><a href="connectors.html"><strong>Connectors</strong></a> -
    Connectors available in JBoss Web, and native web server integration.</li>
<li><a href="monitoring.html"><strong>Monitoring and Management</strong></a> -
    Enabling JMX Remote support, and using tools to monitor and manage JBoss Web.</li>
<li><a href="logging.html"><strong>Logging</strong></a> -
    Configuring logging in JBoss Web.</li>
<li><a href="apr.html"><strong>Apache Portable Runtime</strong></a> -
    Using APR to provide superior performance, scalability and better
    integration with native server technologies.</li>
<li><a href="virtual-hosting-howto.html"><strong>Virtual Hosting</strong></a> -
    Configuring vitual hosting in JBoss Web.</li>
<li><a href="aio.html"><strong>Advanced IO</strong></a> -
    Extensions available over regular, blocking IO.</li>

</ol>

</section>


<section name="Reference">

<p>The following documents are aimed at <em>System Administrators</em> who
are responsible for installing, configuring, and operating a JBoss Web server.
</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="RELEASE-NOTES.txt"><strong>Release notes</strong></a>
    - Known issues in this JBoss Web release.
    </li>
<li><a href="config/index.html"><strong>JBoss Web Server Configuration Reference</strong></a>
    - Reference manual that documents all available elements and attributes
      that may be placed into a JBoss Web <code>conf/server.xml</code> file.
    </li>
<li><a href="http://tomcat.apache.org/connectors-doc/index.html"><strong>JK Documentation</strong></a>
    - Complete documentation and HOWTOs on the JK native webserver connector,
      used to interface JBoss Web with servers like Apache HTTPd, IIS
      and others.</li>
<li><a href="servletapi/index.html"><strong>Servlet API Javadocs</strong></a> -
    The Servlet 3.0 API Javadocs.</li>
<li><a href="jspapi/index.html"><strong>JSP API Javadocs</strong></a> -
    The JSP 2.2 API Javadocs.</li>
</ul>

</section>


<section name="JBoss Web Developers">

<p>The following documents are for Java developers who wish to contribute to
the development of the <em>JBoss Web</em> project.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="building.html"><strong>Building from Source</strong></a> -
    Details the steps necessary to download JBoss Web source code (and the
    other packages that it depends on), and build a binary distribution from
    those sources.
    </li>
<li><a href="changelog.html"><strong>Changelog</strong></a> - Details the
    changes made to JBoss Web.
    </li>
<li><a href="catalina/docs/api/index.html"><strong>Catalina Javadocs</strong></a>
    - Javadoc API documentation for the <em>Catalina</em> servlet
    container and its dependencies.</li>
<li><a href="jasper/docs/api/index.html"><strong>Jasper Javadocs</strong></a>
    - Javadoc API documentation for the <em>Jasper</em> JSP container
    portion of JBoss Web.</li>
<li><a href="architecture/index.html"><strong>JBoss Web Architecture</strong></a>
    - Documentation of the JBoss Web Server Architecture.</li>

</ul>

</section>


</body>
</document>
