<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document url="host.html">

  &project;

  <properties>
    <author email="craigmcc@apache.org">Craig R. McClanahan</author>
    <author email="remm@apache.org">Remy Maucherat</author>
    <author email="yoavs@apache.org">Yoav Shapira</author>
    <author email="jfclere@gmail.com">Jean-Frederic Clere</author>
    <title>The virtual-server element</title>
  </properties>

<body>


<section name="Introduction">

  <p>The <strong>virtual-server</strong> element represents a <em>virtual host</em>,
  which is an association of a network name for a server (such as
  "www.mycompany.com" with the particular server on which Catalina is
  running.  In order to be effective, this name must be registered in the
  <em>Domain Name Service</em> (DNS) server that manages the Internet
  domain you belong to - contact your Network Administrator for more
  information.</p>

  <p>In many cases, System Administrators wish to associate more than
  one network name (such as <code>www.mycompany.com</code> and
  <code>company.com</code>) with the same virtual host and applications.
  This can be accomplished using the <a href="#Host Name Aliases">Host
  Name Aliases</a> feature discussed below.</p>

  <p>One or more <strong>virtual-server</strong> elements are nested inside an
  <a href="subsystem.html">subsystem=web</a> element.</p>

</section>


<section name="Attributes">

  <subsection name="Common Attributes">

    <p>The <strong>virtual-server</strong>
    supports the following attributes:</p>

    <attributes>

      <attribute name="name" required="true">
        <p>Name of the Virtual Host</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="alias" required="false">
        <p>List of alias supported by the Virtual Host</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="access-log" required="false">
        <p>Element describing how the access log information should be logged.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="rewrite" required="false">
        <p>Element describing what the rewrite valve should do with requests corresponding to the Virtual Host.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="enable-welcome-root" required="false">
        <p>Whether or not the bundled welcome directory is used as the root web context.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="default-web-module" required="false">
        <p>Webapp to use as default applicationWhether or not the bundled welcome directory is used as the root web context.
           If not specified, a default of <code>ROOT.war</code> is used.</p>
      </attribute>

    </attributes>

  </subsection>


  <subsection name="Standard Implementation">

    <p>virtual-server doesn't support more attributes that the ones listed above.</p>

  </subsection>


</section>


<section name="Nested Components">

  <subsection name="access-log">

    <p><code>access-log</code>describes how the access log information should be logged.
       It adds the <code>AccessLogValve</code> to the Virtual Host defined by <code>virtual-server</code>
       See the <a href="../api/org/apache/catalina/valves/AccessLogValve.html">AccessLogValve api documentation</a> for more information.
    </p>

    <attributes>
      <attribute name="relative-to" required="false">
        <p>directory location based on the global path configuration in the domain model.
           If not specified, it defaults to the JBoss Application data directory (jboss.server.base.dir).</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="path" required="false">
        <p>directory location based on the referenced path.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="pattern" required="false">
        <p>Patern used by the AccessLogValve. The paterns are described in the <a href="../api/org/apache/catalina/valves/AccessLogValve.html">
           AccessLogValve api documentation.</a>
           If not specified, a default of <code>common</code> is used.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="resolve-hosts" required="false">
        <p>Tell the Valve to resolve or not the host names.
           If not specified, a default of <code>false</code> is used.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="extended" required="false">
        <p>Used the <code>ExtendedAccessLogValve</code> instead the <code>AccessLogValve</code>
           If not specified, a default of <code>false</code> is used.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="prefix" required="false">
        <p>Define the prefix to use to name the log file.
           If not specified, a default of <code>access_log.</code> is used.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="rotate" required="false">
        <p>Tell the valve if it should rotate the ouput or not.
           If not specified, a default of <code>true</code> is used.</p>
      </attribute>
    </attributes>

  </subsection>

  <subsection name="rewrite">
    <p><code>rewrite</code>describes how requests should be rewritten before processing.
       It adds the <code>RewriteValve</code> to the Virtual Host defined by <code>virtual-server</code>
       See <a href="../rewrite.html">URL Rewriting</a> for more information.
    </p>

    <attributes>
      <attribute name="condition" required="true">
        <p>list of <code>condition</code>Elements. See condition below.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="pattern" required="true">
        <p>Pattern is a perl compatible regular expression, which is applied to the URL of the request.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="substitution" required="true">
        <p>The substitution of a rewrite rule is the string which is substituted for (or replaces) the original URL which Pattern matched</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="flags" required="true">
        <p>Substitution options (See <a href="../rewrite.html">URL Rewriting</a> for all the available options</p>
      </attribute>
    </attributes>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="condition">
    <attributes>
    <p><code>condition</code>describes a condition of the conditions list to apply the pattern substitution</p>
      <attribute name="test" required="true">
        <p>a test string is first evaluated, before being matched against the specified pattern</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="pattern" required="true">
        <p>CondPattern is the condition pattern, a regular expression which is applied to the current instance of the test string</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="flags" required="true">
        <p>Matching options AND/OR and NC</p>
      </attribute>
    </attributes>
  </subsection>
</section>


</body>


</document>
