<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document url="index.html">

  &project;

  <properties>
    <author email="craigmcc@apache.org">Craig R. McClanahan</author>
    <author email="jfclere@gmail.com">Jean-Frederic Clere</author>
    <title>Overview</title>
  </properties>

<body>


<section name="Overview">

<p>This manual contains reference information about all of the configuration
directives that can be used in the Web subsystem to
configure the behavior of the JBoss Web Servlet/JSP container.  It does not
attempt to describe which configuration directives should be used to perform
specific tasks - for that, see the various <em>HOW-TO</em> documents on the
main index page.</p>

<p>The configuration element descriptions are organized into the following
major categories:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>connectors</strong> - Represent the interface between external
    clients sending requests to (and receiving responses from) a particular
    Service.</li>
<li><strong>virtual-server</strong> - Represent the virtual host corresponding
    to requests matching it.</li>
<li><strong>jsp-configuration</strong> - That is the configuration of 
    the JSP container.</li>
<li><strong>static-resources</strong> - That is the configuration of
    Default Servlet (how the static ressources should served).</li>
<li><strong>Nested Components</strong> - Represent elements that can be
    nested inside the above elements.</li>
</ul>

<p>For each element, the corresponding documentation follows this general
outline:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Introduction</strong> - Overall description of this particular
    component.  There will be a corresponding Java <em>interface</em> (in
    the <code>org.apache.catalina</code> pacakge) that is implemented by one
    or more standard implementations.</li>
<li><strong>Attributes</strong> - The set of attributes that are legal for
    this element.</li>
<li><strong>Nested Components</strong> - Enumerates which of the <em>Nested
    Components</em> can be legally nested within this element.</li>
<li><strong>Special Features</strong> - Describes the configuration of a large
    variety of special features (specific to each element type).</li>
</ul>

</section>


</body>
</document>
